Ramakrishnan Sundara Raman

PhD Candidate, University of Michigan

☑ ramaks@umich.edu

https://ramakrishnansr.com/

in ramakrishnansundararaman

I am a PhD candidate with 5+ years of experience in computer security and networking research. My expertise lies in building empirical methods to detect, analyze and prevent large-scale security and privacy threats to Internet users. My research involves longitudinally measuring Internet censorship and connection tampering at global scale, and examining the technologies that enable tampering. I am a lead researcher for the Censored Planet Observatory, and I am the recipient of a FOCI Rising Star Award, an OTF Information Controls Fellowship, and an IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize.

Education

2018 - Present

PhD Candidate, University of Michigan in Computer Science and Engineering

Advisor: Prof. Roya Ensafi

Thesis title: Global, Longitudinal, and Data-Driven Investigation of Network Restrictions

CGPA: 3.95 out of 4

2013 – 2017 Rachelor of Technology, Vellore Institute of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering

Project Title: Measuring Last-Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather

CGPA: 9.69 out of 10 **Rank in CSE**: 2 out of 648

Conference Publications

Modeling and Detecting Internet Censorship Events

E. Tsai, R. Sundara Raman, A. Prakash, R. Ensafi
Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2024

Global, Passive Detection of Connection Tampering

R. Sundara Raman, L.H. Merino, K. Bock, M. Fayed, D. Levin, N. Sullivan, L. Valenta ACM SIGCOMM, September 2023

O Network Responses to Russia's Invasion of Ukraine in 2022: A Cautionary Tale for Internet Freedom 🔗

R. Ramesh*, **R. Sundara Raman***, A. Virkud, A. Dirksen, A. Huremagic, D. Fifield, D. Rodenburg, R. Hynes, D. Madory, R. Ensafi

USENIX Security Symposium, August 2023

○ CERTainty: Detecting DNS Manipulation using TLS Certificates *§*

E. Tsai, D. Kumar, R. Sundara Raman, G. Li, Y. Eiger, R. Ensafi

Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS), July 2023

O Network Measurement Methods for Locating and Examining Censorship Devices

R. Sundara Raman*, M. Wang*, J.Dalek, J. Mayer, and R. Ensafi

ACM Conference on emerging Networking EXperiments and Technologies (CoNEXT), December 2022

TIRTF Applied Networking Research Prize

O A Large-scale Investigation into Geodifferences in Mobile Apps &

R. Kumar, A. Virkud, R. Sundara Raman, A. Prakash, and R. Ensafi

USENIX Security Symposium, August 2022

Lost in Transmission: Investigating Filtering of COVID-19 Websites

A. Vyas, R. Sundara Raman, N. Ceccio, P. Lutscher, and R. Ensafi

Financial Cryptography and Data Security (FC), March 2021

Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory

R. Sundara Raman, P. Shenoy, K. Kohls, and R. Ensafi

ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), November 2020

○ Investigating Large Scale HTTPS Interception in Kazakhstan 🔗

R. Sundara Raman, L. Evdokimov, E. Wustrow, A. Halderman, and R. Ensafi

ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), October 2020

Best Paper Award Nominee

^{*}Both authors contributed equally to this research

- Measuring the Deployment of Network Censorship Filters at Global Scale <u>R. Sundara Raman</u>, A. Stoll, J. Dalek, R. Ramesh, W. Scott, R. Ensafi
 Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020
- O Decentralized Control: A Case Study of Russia 🔗

R. Ramesh, **R. Sundara Raman**, M. Bernhard, V. Ongkowijaya, L. Evdokimov, A. Edmundson, S. Sprecher, M. Ikram, R. Ensafi

Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020

To CSAW'20 Applied Research Competition North America Top 10 Paper

Workshop Publications

- Advancing the Art of Censorship Data Analysis
 R. Sundara Raman, A. Virkud, S. Laplante, V. Fortuna, R. Ensafi

 Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), February 2023
- O A Multi-Perspective View of Internet Censorship in Myanmar &

R. Padmanabhan, A. Filastò, M. Xynou, **R. Sundara Raman**, K. Middleton, M. Zhang, D. Madory, M. Roberts, and A. Dainotti

Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), August 2021

Awards

Research FOCI'23 Rising Star Award & July 2023

■ IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize (ANRP) 2023

January 2023

HotPETs 2022 Best Talk Award & July 2022

■ University of Michigan CSE Graduate Student Honors Runners Up Award

November 2020

ACM IMC 2020 Best Paper Award Nominee

October 2020

Fellowships & Grants Rackham Predoctoral Fellowship

March 2023

OTF Information Controls Fellowship (ICFP)

November 2021

Travel Grants-ACM IMC 2022, USENIX Security 2020, and Citizen Lab Summer Institute 2019

Teaching & Service North

North Campus Deans' MLK Spirit Award 2023 & January 2023

■ University of Michigan CSE GSI Honorable Mention Award
August 2021

Teaching

Topic: Censorship and Circumvention

January 2023 Substitute Instructor, EECS 588, University of Michigan

Topic: Computer and Network Security

Topic: Censorship and Circumvention

August 2020 – December 2020 📕 Graduate Student Instructor (GSI), EECS 588, University of Michigan

Topic: Computer and Network Security

TGSI Honorable Mention Award

Work Experience

July 2022 - September 2022

Research Intern, Cloudflare Inc.

- Designed a large network monitoring system that identifies anomalous network events such as connection tampering attacks in large-scale network traffic at the rate of millions of packets per second.
- Developed network data analysis methods and tools for detecting large-scale traffic tampering passively from an operator's point of view.
- Built production dashboards and reports showcasing significant network events such as the effects of the protests in Iran on Internet traffic.

November 2021 - July 2022

OTF Senior ICFP Fellow in Information Controls, The Citizen Lab

- Researched novel measurement methods for locating and examining network devices that performed surveillance and censorship.
- Collaborated with the expert team at the Citizen Lab, a research group focused on network forensics.
- Published several open-source tools and fingerprint datasets for identifying censorship devices.

July 2017 - May 2018

Associate Consultant, Microsoft

Contributed to large enterprise systems for business applications that can deliver value to large organizations around the world.

March 2017 - July 2017

Research Intern, University of Maryland

Advisor: Prof. Neil Spring

- Facilitated a measurement platform and analysis tools that identifies last-mile residential Internet outages in areas affected by severe weather conditions in real-time.
- Poster presented at ACM Internet Measurement Conference 2017: "Measuring Last-Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather"

May 2016 - July 2016

■ Intern, Microsoft

Integrated data analytics into Microsoft's project management tool, built on ASP.NET. Microsoft's Power BI tool was utilized to make interactive reports that provided valuable insight to the users.

Mentoring

- Undergraduate Students: Nadav Oren (2023), Apurva Virkud (2020 2022), Anjali Vyas (2020 2021), Rose Ceccio (2020 2021), Prerana Shenoy (2019 2020)
- O Graduate Students: Kevin Wang (2023), Elisa Tsai (2020 2023)

Talks

- Conference Talk: Network Responses to Russia's Invasion of Ukraine in 2022: A Cautionary Tale for Internet Freedom

Usenix Security Symposium, August 2023

- Workshop Talk: Advancing the Art of Censorship Data Analysis
 Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), February 2023
- Lightning Talk: Exploring Internet censorship through the Censored Planet Dashboard
 Open Technology Fund (OTF), January 2023
- O Conference Talk: Network Measurement Methods for Locating and Examining Network Censorship Devices Conference on emerging Networking Experiments and Technologies (CoNEXT 2022), December 2022
- Workshop Talk: Improving Usability of Internet Censorship Data through a Censorship Dashboard
 15th Workshop on Hot Topics in Privacy Enhancing Technologies (HotPETs), July 2022
 Best Talk Award

3

- Tech Demo: Exploring Internet censorship with the Censored Planet Dashboard RightsCon 2022, June 2022
- Symposium Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory
 The 5th Annual Data for Public Good Symposium, March 2022
- Invited Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide Longitudinal Observatory NDSS DNS Privacy Workshop (DNSPriv), February 2021
- Conference Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide Longitudinal Observatory & ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), November 2020

Reports and Blogposts

Measuring Connection Tampering Around the World

Internet Society Pulse Blog, October 2023

https://pulse.internetsociety.org/blog/measuring-connection-tampering-around-the-world

Making Censorship Data More User Friendly

Internet Society Pulse Blog, May 2023

₱ https://pulse.internetsociety.org/blog/making-censorship-data-more-user-friendly

Profiling Internet Censors: Methods to Measure and Locate Censorship Devices

Open Technology Fund (OTF), December 2022

• https://www.opentech.fund/news/profiling-internet-censors-methods-to-measure-and-locate-censorship-devices/

O An analysis of a large-scale HTTPS interception

APNIC Blog, February 2021

https://blog.apnic.net/2021/02/15/an-analysis-of-a-large-scale-https-interception/

 US Government and military websites are geoblocked from Hong Kong and China Censored Planet, August 2020

• https://censoredplanet.org/hongkong

Posters

- Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory Midwest Security Workshop, April 2019
- Measuring Last Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), November 2017

Certifications

- Introduction to Data Science in Python
 Ø
 University of Michigan Coursera, June 2023

Service

Chairing Reviewing

- Session Chair at FOCI'21 &
- TPC Member, IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2024 🔗
- TPC Member, Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI) 2024 &
- Reviewer, 6th International Conference on Computer Science and Application Engineering (CSAE) 2022
- TPC Member, ACM SIGCOMM 2021 Workshop on Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI) 🚱

External Reviewing

- USENIX Security Symposium 2022
- ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC) 2021
- USENIX Security Symposium 2021
- ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC) 2020
- IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2020
- Privacy Enhancing Technology Symposium (PETS) 2020
- USENIX Security Symposium 2019
- IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2019

Leadership

Outreach Chair at CSEG, UM CSE graduate student organization

June 2020 - May 2022

My responsibilities included arranging and managing outreach events throughout the year that aimed at spreading knowledge about computer science research in various schools, colleges and groups. I also participated as the DEI committee student representative of CSEG in early 2022.

T Deans' MLK Spirit Award 2023

Administrator of the Security Reading Group (SECRIT) in UM CSE

June 2019 - June 2021